The 17th day in the Omer. Today's דף daf is דף סמך,
Daf Samach, 60. We pick up in the bottom of middle-bottom of
דף נט עמוד ב Daf Nun Tet Amud Bet and we were
dealing with the fascinating debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish, which is if somebody designates that the effect of
the קידושין kiddushin will take place later, gives the money now but
the effect will take place later, can that be voided merely by
words, or does it need some מעשה? ma'aseh? Not clear what that
מעשה ma'aseh would be, but אתי דיבור ומבטל דיבור. ati dibbur u-mevattel
dibbur. And what we saw is that really ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
agrees that there are some scenarios which are just clearly verbal
and that could be negated, for example, the appointing of a שליח,
shaliach, that is a verbal act that could be negated. But the
difference here is that there was actually an act, the act of
קידושין kiddushin took place, and but it just didn't take effect. So
to what degree is that considered an act or just something abstract
and verbal and to what degree do we say אתי דיבור ומבטל
דיבור? ati dibbur u-mevattel dibbur? Do we say that's in the category
of מעשה? ma'aseh? So the גמרא Gemara had two different versions of
ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish position. One was as I said, he really
is only debating this case. The other had him even debating a
case that a woman who designates a שליח shaliach can't negate the
שליח, shaliach, and that was really like wild because how could somebody
go ahead and like marry me off against my will? תוספות Tosafot
tries to figure that out. Anyway, that clearly is not true. The
גמרא Gemara clearly concludes that if you designate a שליח, shaliach, you
could verbally void the שליחות. shlichus. And the conclusion of the גמרא
Gemara is and let's pick up from there, the גמרא... Gemara... we're
going to four lines from the in the wide lines,
the גמרא Gemara says תיובתא דריש לקיש תיובתא. tiuvta de-Reish Lakish tiuvta.
So we ended with a text that clearly showed that ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish was wrong. It's a contradiction to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish,
that if you verbally designate a שליח, shaliach, you can also verbally
negate it. So if the woman makes a שליח shaliach to receive
קידושין kiddushin for her, she can verbally negate it. So fine, that's
clear. But then the גמרא Gemara says והלכתא כוותיה דרבי יוחנן ואפילו
בקמייתא. ve-hilchesa ke-vatei de-Rabbi Yochanan ve-afillu be-kameita. We rule like רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan even in the first version of their debate, even when
money of קידושין kiddushin was given and the effect was designated for
30 days from now, that can be verbally voided before it takes
effect. And even though you might want to say that's called a
מעשה ma'aseh and that's not a דיבור, dibbur, no, we rule like
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan there as well. As long as the קידושין
kiddushin hasn't taken effect, either party can verbally void it. ואף על
גב דאיכא למימר שאני נתינת ממון ליד האישה דכמעשה דמי, ve-af al
gav de-ika le-meimar shani nesinas mammon le-yad ha-ishah de-kama'aseh dami, and here
the גמרא Gemara spells it out. Even though we've established דיבור dibbur
negates a דיבור, dibbur, but that case might be
different. The actual act of קידושין kiddushin of giving money into the
woman's hands might be considered to be a real act. אפילו הכי
אתי דיבור ומבטל דיבור. afillu hachi ati dibbur u-mevattel dibbur. No, we're
still going to call it a דיבור dibbur because it has not
yet taken effect, and therefore since it hasn't taken
effect, it's still seen as
abstract, there's been no yet change of status. In contrast, for example,
like one of the classic examples that a דיבור dibbur can't be
מבטל mevattel a מעשה ma'aseh was or even cases where a דיבור
dibbur can't be מבטל mevattel a דיבור dibbur is if you decided
you were done making a vessel, so it was considered done and
then it's susceptible for being able to become טמא, tamei, and your
thought to go back and fix it and to work on it
is irrelevant. But there, as Dov correctly pointed out, there was a
status change. The thing was considered a vessel. Okay, here you have
an act that didn't take effect, there was no status change, since
nothing yet has halachically changed, it's still in the category of just
דיבור dibbur and therefore it can verbally be voided, there is not
an act that is necessary to void it. Okay, so nevertheless, so
we said שאני וכו' דכמעשה דמי אפילו הכי אתי דיבור ומבטל דיבור.
shani etc. de-kama'aseh dami, afillu hachi ati dibbur u-mevattel dibbur. Nevertheless, that's
still considered just speech, not yet an act, and words can void
it. Yes, wait a minute, let me just let me just finish
till the two dots. קשיא הלכתא אהלכתא. kashya hilchesa a-hilchesa. Now wait
a minute, we have a contradiction about two ways we have established
as פסקן-ing. pasken אמרת הלכתא כרבי יוחנן, amarta hilchesa ke-Rabbi Yochanan, you
just said we rule like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that you can
void a שליחות, shlichus, you can void the effect of something that
has been postponed, something that's only supposed to take effect later. והלכתא
כרבי יוחנן. ve-hilchesa ke-Rabbi Yochanan. וקיימא לן, ve-kayma lan, but we also
hold הלכתא כרב נחמן, hilchesa ke-Rav Nachman, that in the case of
voiding a שליח הגט, shaliach ha-get, we rule like רב נחמן. Rav
Nachman. What was that issue? Like רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. איבעיא להו,
iba'ya lehu, we raised the question in גיטין: Gittin: מהו שיחזור ויגרש
בו, mahu she-yachzor ve-yigaresh bo, you went ahead and you chased after
the שליח shaliach you sent to divorce your wife and you voided
him, and then the question is fine, the שליחות shlichus is בטל,
battel, but can you reuse the גט? get? The גט get hasn't
been given yet. רב נחמן אומר חוזר ומגרש בו רב ששת אומר
אינו חוזר ומגרש בו. Rav Nachman omer chozer u-megaresh bo, Rav Sheshet
omer eino chozer u-megaresh bo. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says you can
reuse it
and
רב ששת Rav Sheshet says you
can't reuse it. וקיימא לן. ve-kayma lan. The woman isn't divorced yet,
so the גמרא's Gemara's assuming writing a גט get is like giving
the money to the hands of the woman. And as I can
void the קידושין kiddushin before it takes effect, let me void the
actual גט get itself, and therefore the גט get should not be
able to be reused. Okay, so why do we, how can we
rule like רב נחמן? Rav Nachman? So the answer seems to be
pretty obvious, which is what the גמרא Gemara says. The גמרא Gemara
says, נהי דבטליה משום שליחות משום גט לא בטליה. nehi d'batlei mishum
shlichus mishum get lo batlei. No, no, no, no, you voided the
שליחות, shlichus, but the reason you can reuse the גט get is
that you did not void the גט. get. Now, the question is,
okay, what was the גמרא Gemara assuming? Presumably the גמרא Gemara was
though was assuming that the writing of the גט get was like
the giving of the money. In either way nothing has yet taken
effect and therefore the status could still be voided. But the difference
is you can void the קידושין, kiddushin, the money to be reused
to give קידושין kiddushin again, right? And here the גט, get, you
did do something. It was a מעשה. maaseh. Because even though the
woman wasn't divorced, there was a status change that occurred when you
wrote the גט. get. This piece of paper had a halachic status
of a גט, get, right? So there the act of writing the
גט get actually created something. It turns this into a גט. get.
So that's a מעשה. maaseh. So that's something that actually has been
concretized. That can't be voided with words. Okay when I give the
woman the money, I didn't change the status of the money, I
didn't change the status of the woman, everything has been postponed to
the future. So then I can void it. But here I've created
here and now, I've created a usable גט. get. And that cannot
be voided with words, so it's actually quite consistent that we rule
like רב נחמן Rav Nachman but we also rule that you can
void the קידושין. kiddushin. Yes?
Writing a גט get is like designating something as תרומה terumah in
that sense.
Yeah, exactly, or sure, making something into a כלי, kli, being מפריש
תרומה. mafrish terumah.
So like תפילה tefilla is a מעשה maaseh or a דיבור? dibbur?
What? Saying seriously, no seriously, in other words, if it's a
דיבור, dibbur,
then how can it be that it will be next day for
me if I דאוון מעריב davon Maariv early?
In other words, oh that is such a definition. That is not
to לחול אחר זמן. l'chal achar zman. That's like when you're already
in the hour before nightfall it's considered enough nightfall. You're not having
it take effect לאחר זמן. l'achar zman. It's a cute comparison but
it's not the same. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רב, Amar Rav, now, מקודשת לשני. mekudeshes l'sheni.
Now, the guy says it'll take place after thirty days and somebody
comes and before the thirty days is up, he gives, he marries
the woman before the thirty days is up, she's married to the
second
guy. אמר רב, Amar Rav, מקודשת לשני לעולם. mekudeshes l'sheni l'olam. Yeah,
it's
permanent. The guy number one's act didn't take effect. Guy number two
jumped in. She's married to guy number two, end of story. Guy
number one's out of the picture. ושמואל אמר, u'Shmuel amar, ready for
this? מקודשת לשני עד ל' יום, mekudeshes l'sheni ad lamed yom, until
day thirty she's married to guy number
two. ולאחר ל' יום פקע קידושי שני וגמר קידושי ראשון. u'le'achar lamed
yom paka kiddushei sheni ve'gamar kiddushei rishon. What? No! Don't even get...
basically the way it sounds like, the גמרא's Gemara's going to quickly
reject this because it's too absurd, but the way it sounds like
is guy number one has already staked his claim. Okay? I mean
obviously she's agreed to all of this. His קידושין kiddushin begins on
day thirty. So when guy number two comes along, this woman is
only available to be married until day thirty. Okay? It's not like
the act, you know, it's not like the act of guy number
two negates it. No, she's already been, you know, been already designated
as from day thirty onwards. That status has been fixed. Okay? Unless
guy number one reverses it or woman reverses it. But now you
might say the woman accepting קידושין kiddushin is like her reversing but
who says? She's available for the next twenty days. Okay? And that's
what she married herself off for for the next twenty days. Okay?
Now that's pretty amazing. It flips into a marriage.
All right, so it's pretty,
so let's take a look. The גמרא's Gemara's going to be a
little bit shocked with
this. Okay? So אמר ליה רב יוסף, Amar leh Rav Yosef, so
I'm sorry, the גמרא Gemara says like this, יתיב רב חסדא וקשיא
ליה, yasiv Rav Chisda v'kashya leh, קידושי שני במאי פקע? kiddushei sheni
be'mai paka? I don't get it, he says. How could you, how
could a marriage end without a גט get or without death? Okay?
So he doesn't believe this idea that a woman could be available
to be married for a certain period of time then afterwards automatically
the marriage stops. Okay? Marriage define, you know, is a, is a
relationship that can only be severed, you know, with a גט get
or with marriage, or with death. Like for example, why doesn't a
person just say, you know, I'm married to you for this next
year and it should end at the end of the year? You
have a קידושין לזמן, kiddushin l'zman, right? We never heard of such
a thing. You can't decide to terminate it automatically. It needs something
to change that status. That's the first
משנה, mishna, right? קונה את עצמה בגט ובמיתת הבעל. kona es atzma
beget u'vemisas habaal. You can't pre-designate. Now it's different than selling something.
Because I can actually sell you something for a limited period of
time. I can sell you my, you know, my like Hong Kong
for ninety-nine years, right? I can sell you my land for a
year, and at the end of the year, well no, lease is
different. Lease is I own it and you borrow it. You're renting
it. You have rights to it. But I actually can sell you
something for a period of time. I mean in the גמרא Gemara
also has cases where I can sort of give you as a
deathbed bequest or whatever I can say this plot is ראובן's Reuven
and then after ראובן Reuven it'll pass on to שמעון Shimon and
after שמעון Shimon whatever
to לוי. Levi. So in property and objects you actually might be
able to time things and limit and that at a certain end
of a certain period of time the ownership of that person ends.
But by קידושין Kiddushin we never heard of such a thing. It's
death or divorce so how could this happen? We'll start with Charlie,
yes.
So a temporary marriage is רב Rav is the rabbi who had
temporary marriages? Right. And now it says שמואל Shmuel who advocated temporary...
That's interesting, but רב Rav would end those marriages with a גט
Get or
with
his death, although that would probably be less convenient. Yes. Did you
have a question? All right. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like
this:
Did you think of מיאון? Mi'un?
Yeah, מיאון Mi'un is a good example, although מיאון Mi'un works only
on a rabbinic marriage and מיאון Mi'un also works conceptually as retroactively
reversing it. Although רב חיים Rav Chaim has a sort of brilliant,
I mean, read of what מיאון Mi'un works and actually fits very
well with the sources. And רב חיים Rav Chaim says, I just
can't resist saying this just because it's like so funny to say
this line, he says: מיאון Mi'un works
מכאן ולהבא למפרע, mikan u-le'haba l'mafreia, which means from the point of
מיאון Mi'un on we view it as if she was never married.
But if we consider what happened before the act of מיאון, Mi'un,
we view it that she was married. So in terms of assessing
the nature of the relationship prior to מיאון, Mi'un, we don't say
they were living in sin, right, we say that they were married
at that time, but relating to anything moving forward we view it
as if she was never married. But anyway, מיאון Mi'un is an
interesting example somewhat of that, but it works in theory retroactively and
it's all rabbinic. Okay. So anyway, that's the question. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר ליה רב יוסף.
amar leh Rav Yosef. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef said to רב
חסדא, Rav Chisda, מר רישא מתני לה. mar reisha matni leh. You
taught this debate of רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel on the first
case of the משנה, Mishnah, where the second guy comes and marries
her before the end of thirty days. דקשיא ליה, de-kashya leh, and
therefore you had this big problem that שמואל Shmuel makes absolutely no
sense. רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, סיפא מתני לה. seifa matni leh. But
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda teaches the debate of רב Rav and שמואל
Shmuel on the second part of the משנה. Mishnah. ולא קשיא ליה,
ve-lo kashya leh, and he doesn't have a problem. What was the
second part of the משנה? Mishnah? מעכשיו ולאחר שלשים יום. me-achshav u-le'achar
sheloshim yom. Not the case where the guy said after thirty days.
The guy said starting now and ending in thirty days. And remember
what the משנה Mishnah said when guy number two came along, that
it was ספק safek who she was married to. Okay, right? Everybody
remember that in the משנה? Mishnah? Right, guy number one says as
of now and the end of thirty days. So what does that
mean? Does it mean as of now? Does it mean at the
end of thirty days? Does it mean it's sort of like an
ongoing process that begins now and ends in thirty days? Very hard
to know exactly what her status is in the middle. So therefore
when the guy number two marries her, then she is ספק מקודשת
safek mekudeshet to guy number one and guy number two. That's what
the משנה Mishnah said. On that case of the משנה, Mishnah, here's
where you have the debate of רב Rav and שמואל. Shmuel. Okay,
let's take a look. מעכשיו ולאחר שלשים יום. me-achshav u-le'achar sheloshim yom.
אמר רב מקודשת ואינה מקודשת לעולם. amar Rav mekudeshet ve-einah mekudeshet le'olam.
This status when guy number two marries her during this thirty days
that she's ספק safek who she's married to, that's a permanent status.
We don't know: was she really married to guy number one, was
she not yet married to guy number one so guy number two
was able to jump
in? ושמואל אמר מקודשת ואינה מקודשת אלא עד שלשים יום. ve-Shmuel amar
mekudeshet ve-einah mekudeshet ella ad sheloshim yom. This ספק safek status is
until day thirty. And what happens at day
thirty? לאחר שלשים יום פקעי קידושי שני וגמרי קידושי ראשון. le'achar sheloshim
yom paki kiddushei sheni ve-gamri kiddushei rishon. Not like we said before,
right, after thirty days, you know, well whatever. It doesn't matter, I
won't confuse you, but after thirty days guy number two gets pushed
out and guy number one now becomes effective, right? Because guy number
one said... okay, here's guy number one and he said מעכשיו, me-achshav,
now, okay, ולאחר שלשים יום, u-le'achar sheloshim yom, until day thirty. And
guy number two jumped in here,
and
he tried to marry her here. Okay, so we say that during
this period it's a ספק safek who she's married to because this
is some type of a... but what happens when day number thirty
comes? שמואל Shmuel is reading
מעכשיו ולאחר שלשים me-achshav u-le'achar sheloshim means
מעכשיו. ולאחר שלשים me'achshav ve'le'achar sheloshim says שמואל Shmuel is a תנאי.
tenai. When day thirty occurs and I'm still alive or neither of
us have backed out, because day thirty will eventually
occur. So what type of a... no, right. So רש"י Rashi basically
says the תנאי tenai is we haven't backed out or I haven't
died or whatever, okay, we're still all around and agreeing for it.
When day thirty occurs, retroactively you'll be married to me מעכשיו. me-achshav.
If that's true, when guy number two marries her, it's only a
ספק safek who she's married to until day thirty, because before day
thirty maybe, you know, the תנאי tenai won't be satisfied, maybe guy...
guy number one will reverse himself, maybe guy number one will die,
who knows? Okay. But so the ספק safek is only until then.
But once you hit day thirty, guy number then it's then it's
all guy number one and guy number two gets kicked out. So
that's why שמואל Shmuel says the ספק safek status is only until
day thirty, because according to שמואל, Shmuel, this statement is a תנאי.
tnai. Now, why according to רב Rav is it an ongoing ספק
safek status? Okay, even when day thirty arrives. So there's two ways
of understanding it. One is what the גמרא Gemara is not going
to say, but we're going to see in a minute that position,
that מעכשיו ולאחר שלשים me'achshav u'l'achar shloshim, is some ongoing... it begins
now and it sort of it continues and finishes in thirty days.
So if that's true, in the middle, it's not a ספק safek
what it was. It was always quasi-married to guy number one. Right
everybody get that? It was she was always quasi-married to guy number
one and it wasn't a hundred percent till the end, but by
then guy number two had jumped in. So therefore it's always this
grey area. What does it mean to be quasi-married and was guy
number two able to marry her in that status in which she
was in that quasi status or not? That's one possibility, which we'll
get to. That's not what the גמרא Gemara is going to say
what רב Rav is going to say. The גמרא Gemara is going
to say what רב Rav is going to say is רב Rav
says it's either or. Either שמואל Shmuel is right and it's a
תנאי, tnai, so when day number thirty occurs, retroactively she was married
from the beginning. Or מעכשיו me-achshav. doesn't really mean מעכשיו. me'achshav Since
he ended it by saying ולאחר שלשים, u-le'achar sheloshim he really meant
לאחר שלשים. le'achar sheloshim. That's a pretty hard read, because what does
מעכשיו me'achshav. mean? So maybe he changed his mind. Anyway, so either
it means as of now, it's all now, or it's all later.
One or the other. One of the two extremes. We don't know
which one. So in that case, she remains
בספק לעולם. be'safek le'olam. Okay. So that's the debate of רב Rav
and שמואל. Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel says it means now, the ספק safek
is only until day thirty arrives, once day thirty arrives, clearly guy
number one. And רב Rav says it's always a ספק safek what
he means and she's always going to be a ספק safek who
she's married to.
Think about this understanding רב's Rav פירוש. peirush. In other words, from
this minute, as of this second, thirty days from now we'll be
married.
In
other words, in other words, right... no-no, not how to parse it.
A minute ago, we wouldn't have been married thirty days from now,
but as of this minute...
oh you mean in order to say it means לאחר זמן? le'achar
zeman? Yeah. I'm doing the act מעכשיו... me'achshav maybe. Okay. In other
words, I could see that.
All right,
so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
Okay. Okay. ושמואל אמר מקודשת ואינה מקודשת אלא עד שלשים לאחר שלשים
פקע קידושי שני וגם
קידושי ראשון. u-Shmuel amar mekudeshet ve-eina mekudeshet ela ad sheloshim le-achar sheloshim
paka kiddushei sheini ve-gam kiddushei rishon. ורב מספקא ליה, ve-Rav mesapka lei,
רב Rav doesn't know, אי תנאי הוי, i tnai havei, is לאחר
שלשים יומא תנאי? le'achar sheloshim yoma tnai? And therefore when thirty days
hits, it'll only have been guy number one and guy number two
will be out of the picture. That's what שמואל Shmuel says. אי
חזרה הוי, i chazara havei, or when he says שלשים sheloshim he's
backing away from the מעכשיו me'achshav... and it's all לאחר שלשים יום
le'achar sheloshim yom and therefore guy number two always got in and
stays in and guy number one is out of the picture. So
we don't know, it's either all one or all two, we don't
know she's בספק. be'safek. ולשמואל פשיטא ליה דתנאי הוי u-le-Shmuel peshita lei
de-tnai havei and שמואל Shmuel thinks no, clearly it's a תנאי tnai
and therefore the ספק safek is only until day thirty hits, but
once day thirty hits it's clearly guy number one. Okay. וביפלוגתא דהני
תנאי, u-bi-plugta de-hanei tanna'ei, this is exactly like the debate of the
following
תנאים, tanna'im, דתניא de-tanya we
taught in the
ברייתא, braisa, מהיום ולאחר מיתה גט ואינו גט. me-hayom ve-le'achar mita get
ve-eino get. Here's the גט, get, take effect now and it ends
after I die. Okay. So it's a ספק, safek, דברי חכמים. divrei
chachamim. רבי אומר כזה גט. Rabbi omer kazei get. Now, how could
it be a ספק? safek? If I say it takes effect after
I die, there's not a גט לאחר מיתה. get le'achar mita. So
the ספק safek is, do I mean as of now assuming I
die, you know, from this illness? Somebody's trying to save his wife
from having to undergo יבום. yibum. So it'll take effect as of
now assuming I die, that's a תנאי, tnai, and then it would
be good. Or do I say it means as of now, you
know what, no, actually rather after I die? Okay. Is it a
תנאי tnai or is it
לאחר שלשים... le'achar sheloshim... לאחר מיתה? le'achar mita? And then it's a
ספק. safek. That's רב's Rav position. רבי Rabbi says it totally works,
meaning רבי Rabbi doesn't have any question. It definitely is a גט
get and if the guy dies during this illness, it'll definitely be
a גט. get. So it seems the debate of רב Rav and
שמואל Shmuel is exactly the debate of the חכמים chachamim and
רבי. Rabbi. Okay. ונימא רב הלכה כרבנן ונימא שמואל הלכה כרבי. ve-neima
Rav halacha ke-rabbanan ve-neima Shmuel halacha ke-rabbi. So just say you're פסקנינג
paskening like רב Rav is פסקנינג paskening like the רבנן rabbanan and
שמואל Shmuel is פסקנינג paskening like
רבי. Rabbi. צריכא, tzricha, no-no-no, because the cases are not exactly parallel.
You need to have both
discussions. דאי אמר רב הלכה כרבנן, de-i amar Rav halacha ke-rabbanan, had
you say we rule like the רבנן rabbanan by the גט get
that it's a
ספק, safek, הוה אמינא התם דחומרא קאתי, hava amina hatam de-chumra ka-atei,
there where... He's divorcing her, distancing himself from her, he's more reluctant
to do it. So maybe he really means after I die and
it's not just a
תנאי. Tnai. אבל הכא דקירובא קאתי, Aval hacha d'kurvaka asi, here where
he's trying to marry her, אימא מודה ליה לשמואל, eima modei lei
l'Shmuel, I'm more inclined to read the language as a תנאי tnai
because he really means מהשתא. me'ashta. He wants to marry her, you
don't want to push it
off. דתנאי הוי, D'tnai hvei, so therefore you have to tell me
that he says even in the case of קידושין kiddushin it's a
ספק. safek. ואי אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי, V'ei amar Shmuel halacha k'Rebbe,
if שמואל Shmuel said we rule like רבי Rebbe by a גט
Get that it means
מהשתא, me'ashta, הווה אמינא התם דאין גט לאחר מיתה, hava amina hasam
d'ein get l'achar misa, there of course it means מהשתא me'ashta because
a גט Get doesn't take effect after the guy dies. So obviously
he means as of
now. אבל הכא דיש קידושין לאחר ל', Aval hacha d'yesh kiddushin l'achar
lamed, but here where קידושין kiddushin could take effect after 30 days,
so maybe he really means not as of now, he means after
30 days. אימא מודה ליה לרב, Eima modei lei l'Rav, maybe he'd
agree to רב. Rav. צריכא, Tzricha, you have to tell me both
cases. Okay, but either way if you say as of now and
after 30 or as of now and after and at time X,
so רב Rav says it's a ספק safek whether you mean now
or later, and שמואל Shmuel says you definitely mean now and it's
a תנאי. tnai. Okay, and there's a third possibility which we're going
to say which is no, you really mean some ongoing way. Let's
take a look. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says like
this. צריכא. Tzricha. אמר אביי ולטעמי דרב, Amar Abaye u'l'ta'amei d'Rav, according
to
רב, Rav, בא אחד ואמר לה הרי את מקודשת לי מהיום ולאחר
ל' יום, ba echad v'amar lah harei at mekudeshes li me'hayom u'l'achar
lamed yom, remember רב Rav is the ספק. safek. ובא אחר ואמר
לה הרי את מקודשת לי מהיום ולאחר כ' יום, u'va acher v'amar
lah harei at mekudeshes li me'hayom u'l'achar esrim yom, ובא אחר ואמר
לה הרי את מקודשת לי מהיום ולאחר י' ימים. u'va acher v'amar
lah harei at mekudeshes li me'hayom u'l'achar asara yamim. Okay, מראשון ומאחרון
צריכה גט, mi'rishon u'mi'acharon tzricha get, מאמצעי אינה צריכה גט. mi'emtzai eina
tzricha get. Okay, so this is a fun case. I thought I
had more markers up here. Every time I bring out my markers,
they always disappear.
Anyway, I know,
but then I've got to get one of those pocket protectors and
I'll look
even
nerdier than I already am. Yes, thank you. So guy number one
says, okay, as of now and after day 30, and then guy
number two jumps in right afterwards and he says as of now
and after day 20, and then let's just use the other
one.
No, good.
And guy number three says, except that doesn't work. All right, and
that's fine, fine. And guy number three says guy number three says
as of now and after day 10. Okay, so שמואל Shmuel says
you only need a גט get according to רב Rav from guy
number one and guy number three. Why? Either all of these statements
mean to take effect
later. If they all mean to take effect later, who's the first
guy whose took effect?
Guy
number three because everybody else's effect was postponed, right? So she's married
to guy number three. Everybody else was later. If it all means
as of now, בתנאי b'tnai that that day arrives, so which one
took effect first? Guy number one. Guy number two either way isn't
married to her, so he doesn't need a גט get from guy
number
two. Okay. מראשון ומאחרון צריכה גט, mi'rishon u'mi'acharon tzricha get, מאמצעי אינה
צריכה גט. mi'emtzai eina tzricha get. ממה נפשך, M'ma nafshach, אי תנאי
הוי, ei tnai hvei, if it means a תנאי, tnai, it means
a תנאי tnai by
everybody, דקמא קידושין, d'kama kiddushin, the first one is קידושין kiddushin because
it starts now and he got there first. דהנך לאו קידושין, D'hanach
lav kiddushin, the other ones they did their act later. אי חזרה
הוי, Ei chazara hvei, if he's reversing the מהשתא me'ashta and it
means at that later time, you know, then דבתרא קידושין, d'basra kiddushin,
then the last guy, his one took effect first after 10 days.
דהנך לאו קידושין, D'hanach lav kiddushin, and the later guys did not,
they were too late. So גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obvious! What's
the חידוש chiddush about this? Other than that it was a fun
example. מהו דתימא האי לישנא משמע תנאי ומשמע חזרה, mahu d'teima hai
lishna mashma tnai u'mashma chazara, it's not that this language means there's
always the question. When we say, "What does this mean?", are we
trying to figure out what you personally meant by it? And if
it's what you personally meant by it, somebody else could use the
same language and mean something else. Or are we saying, "No, no,
no, this only has one legal meaning but we somehow haven't decided
what that legal meaning is," which is bizarre, just make up your
mind and decide what the legal meaning is. But okay, but that's
what it's saying. If it's a question about what you personally meant,
then it's possible that guy number two is married. Why? Because guy
number two meant מהשתא me'ashta and he got in here, and guy
number one and guy number three meant at the end of the
period, right? You see how that's possible? So if it's what you
personally meant, it could have been any of them. All right. So
האי לישנא משמע תנאי ומשמע חזרה. Hai lishna mashma tnai u'mashma chazara.
It was that this language has a legitimate can legitimately mean one
or
the other, וקיבלה קידושין מכולהו, v'kibla kiddushin mi'kulehu, and everybody would have
to give her a גט get because everybody would be a possible
interpretation. Any one of them could have meant מהשתא me'ashta and the
other two could have meant לאחר זמן, l'achar zman, right? And then
the one who meant מהשתא me'ashta would have been the one she
needed a גט get from. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that
we don't say that. we say that we only have one meaning
of this, we have to figure out what its meaning is, but
there's only one legal meaning of this.
That's a really interesting, that's a really interesting idea that we have,
I don't know whatever the cases would be parallel to this. Yeah.
We're going to take language out of the realm of human experience
and we're going to...
Well we have to do that.
But we
don't always do that like in נזיר. Nazir.
We do that all the time, exactly. And a legal system has
to do that, right? You write something in a contract. Oh, let's
figure out what you meant by that phrase. There has to be
legal terms that have clear fixed meanings. And it's like a דברים
שבלב אינם דברים devarim she'belev einam devarim type of an idea too,
you know?
Right.
That's also true, right. You know, so the question is, you know,
that gets to a question that a guy under the חופה chuppah
says הרי את... harei at... the ראשונים Rishonim and the פוסקים Poskim
deal with it in a time when, you know, when women were
not literate in Hebrew. And the guy under the חופה chuppah said
הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, you know, whatever, and
did she really know what he was saying, right? So how much,
you know, well, she said yes, and it was pretty... I mean,
so it gets to interesting questions, you know, right, about if there's
clear evidence you don't know what the guy is talking about, right,
so then it doesn't work. But otherwise, if it's a legal term,
look, the same way I guess the point is, the same way
we say we don't care what he was thinking, we don't care
what she was thinking. You know, you use the term, we give
it a legal meaning, everybody agreed to it. The rest is דברים
שבלב, devarim she'belev, right? So the same way he says, well, I
meant מעכשיו me'achshav even though you're telling me it doesn't matter, the
same would be true by her. But I guess your point is
right, if we thought that it was open for interpretation and we
were going to ask him what he thought, we probably would have
to ask her what she was thinking also, right? But the answer
at the end of the day, we don't care what either of
them was thinking, we care what הלכתית halachikly we say the phrase
means. Yes. And so
that gets to the heart of the difference in נזיר, Nazir, where
we do care more about what you're thinking because נזיר Nazir is
only one person. 100%. 100%, right. The principle of דברים שבלב אינם
דברים devarim she'belev einam devarim is absolutely, does not apply by things
like נזיר Nazir and נדר neder and הפלאה. hafla'ah. There the principle
is עד שפיו ולבו שוין, ad she'piv v'libo shavin, the exact opposite
of דברים שבלב אינם דברים. devarim she'belev einam devarim. And certainly one
of the explanations for that, I mean, it could just be that
that's an entire unique category on its own, but the explanation you
just said is something that a number of ראשונים Rishonim say is
true also in other areas, that when something is more one-sided, we
do more care what you're thinking. So for example, רמב"ם Rambam and
the תוספות רי"ד, Tosafot Rid, but you know, רמב"ם Rambam is a
little bigger authority, anyway, but the תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid says it
more explicitly, basically says that when you give a gift or when
you give a גט, get, which are both fundamentally one-sided transactions, we
do more care what you were thinking and less with objectively what,
you know, it means. Okay, so let's take a look. אמר עולא,
Amar Ulla, so now we have a debate that either it's definitely
תנאי tnai
or
it's a ספק תנאי ספק חזרה. safek tnai safek chazarah. Now we
have possibility number
three. עולא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ulla amar Rabbi Yochanan, עולא Ulla says
in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אפילו מאה תופסים בה,
afilu me'ah tofsim bah, a hundred people could be married to her,
okay, in this case of לאחר זמן. l'achar zman. וכן אמר רב
אסי אמר רבי יוחנן אפילו מאה תופסים בה, v'chen amar Rav Assi
amar Rabbi Yochanan afilu me'ah tofsim bah, a hundred people could be
married to her. And רש"י Rashi says it doesn't mean a hundred
people could do it and it's a ספק safek which one, which
would sort of be the idea we were rejecting
here, right, that it could mean something different for every person, so
any one of them could have been the מעכשיו me'achshav person. No,
רש"י Rashi says that's not what we're going to assume. Because if
he says a hundred people are married, he doesn't mean any one
of a hundred and we don't know which one. It sounds like
ממש mamash a hundred people could be married to her. So how
is this going to work? Okay, so אמר ליה רב משרשיא בריה
דרב אמי לרב אסי, Amar lei Rav Mesharshiya breih d'Rav Ami l'Rav
Assi, let me explain to you the position of
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. שוותה נפשה כי שרגא דלבני, Shavtah nafshah k'sharga
d'livni, she made herself basically like bricks on a, that are being
like, you know, that are like a row of bricks, דכל חד
וחד רווחא לחבריה שביק, d'chol chad v'chad ravcha l'chavreih shavik, everybody's leaving
over some space for the next guy. So the metaphor is, when
you lay bricks, very nice little רש"י Rashi describes how you lay
bricks, anyway, I'm serious. Anyway, so when you lay bricks you do
this, right, and then the next row is like this, right? So
anytime when you're laying, right, you're leaving over space so that the
next row can start a little bit in. I don't know exactly
what that metaphor is exactly supposed to say, but the concept being
that עולא Ulla says that it actually means starting now and continuing
and ending later, right? It will take
effect מעכשיו ולאחר me'achshav ule'achar שלשים, it begins now and it starts
later. So when guy number two arrives, okay, she's not fully married
to guy number one yet, okay? And when he says after twenty
days, he's leaving over space for the next guy, because so the
next guy comes and she's not yet fully married to guy number
one and she's not yet, you see this actually does look like
a row of bricks, right? So maybe there you go. Okay, so
right. So anyway, so he's leaving over space because it's not yet
ended here and it's not yet ended and every next guy. So
basically what he is saying is, is that the קידושין kiddushin does
not all take effect now and does not all take effect later,
it's... ongoing, and since it's ongoing, every next guy that comes before
anybody, any particular one has ended, is marrying a woman that is
not yet a hundred percent married. Okay. And he's got enough ability
to sort of jump in there, you know, whatever. So the funny
of course thing is, yeah, it's a very bizarre phenomenon, right? So
let's take a look. Now.
Now
תוספות Tosafos by the way, if you look at תוספות, Tosafos, אפילו,
Afilu, about eight lines down in the narrow lines, תוספות Tosafos says:
ואם תאמר אמאי אמינא הכא דמקודשת, Veim tomar amai amina hacha demikudeshes,
how could she be married here to all these guys? דאמינא לעיל,
Deamina le'ail, which by the way, the גמרא Gemara isn't suggesting that
she can have sex with all the guys, it basically means she
needs a גט get from every one of them. Okay. אומר לאשה
חצייך מקודשת לי ואינה מקודשת, Omer le'isha chetzyech mekudeshes li ve'eino mekudeshes,
if a guy tries to marry half of a woman and the
other half she could marry somebody else, it doesn't take effect. יש
לומר דהתם מאי טעמא לפי שאינה מתקדשת לחצאים, Yesh lomar dehasam mai
taama lefi she'eina miskadeshes lachetza'im, because you can't marry a half of
a woman. לא שייר בגופא דאשה, Lo sheyar begufa ha'isha, he didn't,
he left over some of the actual, you know, body of the
woman itself, like he's not marrying the full person. אבל הכא לא
שייר בגופא דאשה כלום אלא גמורין כולם, Aval hacha lo sheyar begufa
ha'isha kelum ela gemurin kulam, but here, he didn't marry, he married
her fully, it just hasn't finished yet. Okay. So since the effect
hasn't finished, there's enough space for somebody else to jump in. Go
figure that out. All right. Anyway, but it's the most literal read
of מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום. Me'achshav ule'achar sheloshim yom. So back to
the גמרא. Gemara. מעשה דרב חנינא, Ma'asei deRav Chanina, רב חנינא Rav
Chanina asked of this: מהיום ולאחר מיתה גט ואינו גט. Mehayom ule'achar
misa get ve'eino get.
Okay, this what we said before, this debate of רבי Rebbi and
the רבנן, Rabbanan, as of now and after I die, it's a
גט get and not a גט. get. ומת חולצת ולא מתייבמת. Umes
choletzes velo misyabemes. If he dies, he needs to do חליצה chalitza
and not יבום, yibum, and she needs to do חליצה chalitza and
not יבום. yibum. She can't do יבום yibum because maybe she's divorced.
She can't ignore חליצה chalitza because maybe she wasn't divorced, so she
needs חליצה chalitza and not יבום. yibum. בשלמא לרב מסייע ליה, Bishlama
leRav mesayeya lei, according to רב Rav this is good because according
to רב Rav it's a ספק, safek, if it means now then
it was a גט, get, if it means later, it's
a
not a גט, get, so we don't know, so she does חליצה
chalitza and not יבום. yibum. לשמואל נמי הא מני רבנן היא, LeShmuel
nami ha mani Rabbanan hi, according to שמואל Shmuel he would say
yes, that's the רבנן, Rabbanan, the רבנן Rabbanan don't know if it's
מעכשיו me'achshav or if it's לאחר זמן, le'achar zeman, so it's a
ספק. safek. ואנן איי דאמר תנאי, Va'anan ayi de'amar tenai, remember שמואל
Shmuel says מעכשיו me'achshav ולאחר means it's a תנאי, tenai, דאמר כרבי,
de'amar keRebbi, I say like רבי, Rebbi, we quoted earlier, רבי Rebbi
says כזה גט. kezeh get. אלא רבי יוחנן דאמר שיורא הוי, Ela
Rebbi Yochanan de'amar shiyura havei, but רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan who says
that it's a, that it is not, that it is like you're
leaving over space, it began and it didn't get completed, כל גיטא
דמשייר בה ולאו כלום הוא יבמה מי מיבם, Kol gita demishayar bah
velo kelum hu, yevama mi meyabem, any גט get that is not
yet completed, right? It's not like לאחר שלושים, le'achar sheloshim, if there's
no ספק safek what you mean, if you actually mean that it
ends after the, when the end date arrives. So this גט get
by the time the end date arrives, the guy was dead. Okay.
So therefore, and a גט get can't take effect after he's dead.
Effect can only take effect when the husband is alive. So therefore,
if there's no ספק safek here, according to your שמואל, Shmuel, it
must mean that it finished when he was dead, but then it's
not a כשר kosher גט. get. So what's the ספק safek that
she might be מגורשת? megureshes?
So the גמרא Gemara says, so she should just ודאי vadai not
be מגורשת megureshes and just do
יבום. yibum. אמר רבא גט להוציא ומיתה להוציא. Amar Rava, get lehotzi'a
umisa lehotzi'a. No, no, no, here actually it works when he dies,
because the purpose of a גט, get, it's to sever their relationship,
to, it divorces her, and death severs the relationship. מה ששייר גט
גמר מיתה. Ma sheshiyer get gamar misa. We're making up all new
things right and left here, right? So this גט get divorced her
ninety-eight percent, and then he died, okay, and at that moment the
מיתה misa finished off the last two percent. All right. So the
גמרא Gemara says, of course the point is that we know she's
not married to the guy because he's dead. The question is is
she a widow or is she a מגורשת? megureshes? How can you
say the death finishes off the גט get and makes her a
מגורשת, megureshes, right? Which is what אביי Abaye says. אמר ליה אביי
מי דמי, Amar lei Abaye mi dami, how could you compare? גט
מוציא מרשות יבם, Get motzi'a mereshus yavam, the גט get divorces her
and takes her out of the control of the, of the brother,
okay, of the brother-in-law, because then she's a מגורשת. megureshes. מיתה מכנסת
לרשות יבם, Misa machnesa lereshus yavam, the מיתה misa makes her have
a relationship with the brother-in-law. You can't say the death finishes the
process of her being divorced. Okay. The death makes her no longer
married, but it doesn't finish the process of her being divorced. אלא
אמר אביי, Ela amar Abaye, so אביי Abaye says no, התם טעמא
מאי. hasam taama mai. There you know what, you're right. According to
רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan to עולא, Ulla, she's ודאי vadai not divorced,
because he sees מעכשיו ולאחר זמן me'achshav ule'achar zeman as a process,
and since he died before the end of the process, she's not
divorced at all. So the fact that she's not divorced at all,
why not just go ahead and do יבום? yibum? So here's the
reason. גזירה משום מהיום אם מתי הרי זה גט, Gezeira mishum mehayom
im masi harei zeh get, because if he says as of today
if I die, it means makes it explicitly a תנאי. tenai. He
says as of today when I die. Then we would say it's
an ongoing process, he died before it ended, so therefore she's ודאי
vadai not
מגורשת. megureshes. Really יבום... yibum... We have to say, you know what?
Don't do יבום, yibbum, do חליצה. chalitzah. Okay? If we let you
do יבום yibbum when you say as of now and when I
die, and people will say, oh, יבום, yibbum, so that sounds like
then people will think that even if she says that, so it
doesn't work when you say as of now when I die, they'll
think when you say as of now if I die doesn't work.
Okay? So in order because the case of if it does work,
then even though this case definitely doesn't work because it was an
ongoing process that didn't complete, nevertheless we have to treat it as
if it did work in order that people should not be confused.
One
minute. So אמר טעמא דגזירה משום מהיום אם מתי הרי זה גט.
amar taama d'gzeira mishum mehayom im mati harei zeh get. So now
the גמרא Gemara says one minute, if we're afraid that people will
mix up the two cases, ונגזור מהיום אם מתי דתחלוץ v'nigzor mehayom
im mati d'tachlotz אטו מהיום ולאחר מיתה. atu mehayom v'leachar mita. Let's
also make the גזירה gzeira in the reverse. If somebody makes a
תנאי tnai and says as of today if I die, so that
would definitely work. As of today if I die. Okay? And therefore
in that case, she doesn't do יבום, yibbum, doesn't do חליצה. chalitzah.
It's a ודאי vadai good גט. get. Well why don't we say,
wait, let's demand that she does חליצה chalitzah in that case because
people will confuse that case with the case of as of today
when I die. Right? People get that? So should I illustrate this?
Okay. Here's the guy in the deathbed. Okay. And here he says
מהיום, mehayom, okay, ולאחר מיתה. v'leachar mita. Okay? So according to רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, it's an ongoing process but it doesn't take effect
until after he dies, so it's no good. So that's a case
where it's no good. That's a case where it takes effect, that's
a case, excuse me, that's a case where, right, it takes effect
after he's dead, it's no good. So that's no גט. get. Okay?
That's no גט. get. And therefore and therefore, okay, that's that case.
If he says מהיום, mehayom, okay, אם מתי, im mati,
okay, right, in that case, right, this took effect לאחר מיתה, leachar
mita, finished לאחר מיתה leachar mita and it's no good. This one
finishes מהיום mehayom and it's a גט. get. Okay, those are the
two scenarios, right? Now what should the הלכה halacha be? In this
case, if it's no גט, get, the הלכה halacha should be יבום,
yibbum, okay, יבום yibbum or חליצה, chalitzah, either one should be fine.
In this case, right, it's a good גט, get, the הלכה halacha
is, right, no יבום, yibbum, right, no יבום, yibbum, no חליצה chalitzah
because it's a good גט, get, right? So what it says is
the following. This case, you know why we can't allow יבום? yibbum?
We can't allow יבום yibbum in this case because you'll confuse it
with this case. Okay? And if you allow יבום yibbum here, you'll
come to allow יבום yibbum here. Okay? So we have to prevent
you from doing יבום yibbum because you'll come to, that's a גזירה,
gzeira, because you'll come to confuse it with this case and do
יבום yibbum in this case and that would really be bad because
in this case it's a גט get and you do יבום, yibbum,
the guy's, it's one of the עריות, arayos, right? So now the
גמרא Gemara says okay, but let's say the same thing. In this
case, let's demand you do חליצה chalitzah because you'll confuse this case
with this case. And since this case you have to do חליצה,
chalitzah, let's demand that you do חליצה chalitzah here. Okay? That's the
question. Got the question? Because you gotta do one here. You can't
just not do anything, you gotta do יבום yibbum or חליצה.
chalitzah. Which one do you do?
So we're not gonna let you do יבום, yibbum, we're gonna force
you to do חליצה. chalitzah. So let's force you to do חליצה
chalitzah here because if we don't, if we let you walk away
here and do nothing, then you'll come to walk away in this
case too. Okay? So that's the גמרא's Gemara's question. So let's take
a look at the answer. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
ונגזור v'nigzor
so the גמרא Gemara says like this. מהיום אם מתי דתחלוץ, mehayom
im mati d'tachlotz, let's demand you do חליצה chalitzah אטו מהיום ולאחר
מיתה atu mehayom v'leachar mita
because of this case. Okay so we'll demand you do חליצה chalitzah
here so you don't confuse it with, and you don't forget to
do חליצה chalitzah over here. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
No, אם אתה אומר חולצת מתייבמת. im ata omer choletzes mityabemes. No
no no. If we tell you to do חליצה chalitzah here, you
might accidentally do יבום yibbum here. Why?
Wait wait listen. But once you're telling me you do חליצה, chalitzah,
you're signaling to me, what do you mean why? You're signaling to
me that it wasn't a good גט, get, that she was actually
a widow because you're demanding I do חליצה, chalitzah, so that could
lead to me doing יבום. yibbum. And that would be a disaster
because in this case she's divorced and it would be an עריות.
arayos. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says one minute. הכי נמי מצאת
דאמר חולצת מתייבמת. hachi nami matzat d'amar choletzes mityabemes. Here too, if
we tell you do חליצה chalitzah you'll come to do יבום. yibbum.
So the גמרא Gemara says big deal! You're allowed to do יבום
yibbum in this case! Okay? מעיקרא דדין m'ikra d'din you're allowed to
do יבום, yibbum, we just said don't do יבום yibbum because it
might lead to this.
I know, every case in, I know, there's tons of חולצת ולא
מתייבמת choletzes v'lo mityabemes so we're not concerned. Yeah exactly, what can
I tell you? This answers this case. So the גמרא Gemara says
תתייבם ואין בכך כלום. tityabbem v'ein bekach klum. Fine. If this case...
To not do ייבום Yibbum and only do חליצה chalitzah does not
lead to any possible problem. This type of a case if we
were to say do חליצה, chalitzah, it would raise too many questions
about the status here and we don't want to do it. So
take it or not, bottom line is the debate is a fascinating
three-way debate of מעכשיו ולאחר שלושים יום me'achshav u'le'achar shloshim yom that
שמואל Shmuel says it definitely means מעכשיו me'achshav and any ספק safek
is only prior to day thirty arriving. רב Rav says it means
either definitely מעכשיו me'achshav or definitely לאחר שלושים, le'achar shloshim, we just
don't know which one and that's also a debate of תנאים Tannaim
about רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabbanan by a גט. get. And
the most interesting one is עולא Ulla in the name of רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan because it means both. It starts now and it
ends after thirty days and it's an ongoing process which means by
the גט get if the process ended after he's dead it definitely
didn't work but it means in the קידושין Kiddushin case if everybody
is alive at the end then everybody could jump in and you
could actually have her somewhat married to a hundred different guys. Okay,
moving on, next משנה. Mishnah. האומר לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי על
מנת שאתן לך מאתיים זוז. ha'omer le'ishah harei at mekudeshes li al
menas she'etten lach masayim zuz. Okay, you're married to me on the
condition that I give you two hundred זוז. zuz. הרי זו מקודשת,
harei zo mekudeshes, so she's married והוא יתן ve'hu yitten as long
as he's got to give the money. על מנת שאתן לך מכאן
ועד שלושים יום, al menas she'etten lach mikan ve'ad shloshim yom, on
the condition I give you within thirty days. נתן לה בתוך שלושים
יום מקודשת, nasan lah besoch shloshim yom mekudeshes, if he gave her
within thirty days she's married, ואם לאו אינה מקודשת, ve'im lav einah
mekudeshes, if not, not. So far it all seems pretty darn obvious.
על מנת שיש לי מאתיים זוז, al menas she'yesh li masayim zuz,
on the condition I have two hundred זוז zuz in my bank
account, הרי זו מקודשת ויש לו. harei zo mekudeshes ve'yesh lo. She's
married presumably he if he does have two hundred זוז zuz in
his bank account. על מנת שאראך מאתיים זוז, al menas she'arech masayim
zuz, now this might be the one thing that at least for
us seems at least a חידוש. chiddush. On the condition I show
you two hundred זוז. zuz. הרי זו מקודשת ויראה לה. harei zo
mekudeshes ve'yareh lah. So she's מקודשת mekudeshes him if he goes ahead
if and well we'll see if if or if and when he
goes ahead and shows her the two hundred זוז. zuz. But that
means but he only has to show her his two hundred זוז.
zuz. I'm not going to give it to you, I'll show you
that I have it. But ואם הראה לה על השולחן, ve'im her'ah
lah al ha'shulchan, at least if he said it's on the table
now which רש"י Rashi says means the גמרא's Gemara going to say
it means he's a he's a money changer. I said I'd show
you two hundred זוז, zuz, I didn't tell you it was my
two hundred זוז, zuz, okay? I'll show you I'll show you a
house full of jewels and then they walk in and they say
and they go to the Metropolitan Museum or something. Okay, so there
you go, אינה מקודשת. einah mekudeshes. She's not married because even though
technically that was what the word said, that's clearly not what he
meant.
Okay, in the case before this was a חידוש. chiddush. In other
words על מנת al menas that I have it,
he doesn't have
to give it to her. Right.
Okay, but that's literally what he said.
No, I understand, but it's a similar to תנאי. tnai. Okay. But
what
all of
these והוא יתן ve'hu yitten or whatever is an 'if' really, we're
saying.
So this is the question. So the real question of this משנה,
Mishnah, which is not being told in the משנה, Mishnah, is how
do you read והוא יתן. ve'hu yitten. Does it mean 'if he
gives' or does it mean 'when he gives'? Okay? So איתמר, itmar,
so that was debated. Now I think that והוא יתן ve'hu yitten
means she's married now as long as he eventually gives. To me
the language suggests תנאי, tnai, but we're going to see that this
is a debate. Okay. איתמר. itmar. רב הונא אמר והוא יתן, Rav
Huna amar ve'hu yitten, which is certainly what רב הונא Rav Huna
said. No, you know, give and when you give it's as of
now. רב יהודה אמר לכשיתן. Rav Yehuda amar lich'sheyitten. Right, so the
language obviously is more רב הונא, Rav Huna, but you know רב
רב יהודה Rav Rav Yehuda says it means 'when you give'. It
only takes effect when the money is given. So which is interesting,
which is the question, על מנת al menas you would think means
as of now on the condition that eventually I do this. But
that's the question, is על מנת כמעכשיו דמי al menas ke'me'achshav dami
or not כמעכשיו דמי? ke'me'achshav dami? So that's exactly what's being debated.
Okay. רב הונא Rav Huna says it means as of now, כמעכשיו,
ke'me'achshav, and רב יהודה Rav Yehuda says it means 'when'. רב הונא
אמר והוא יתן תנאי הוי. Rav Huna amar ve'hu yitten tnai havei.
It's a תנאי. tnai. מקיים תנאיה ואזיל. mekayem tna'eih ve'azil. You do
your תנאי tnai eventually and whenever takes but but it takes effect
as of now. רב יהודה אמר לכשיתן. Rav Yehuda amar lich'sheyitten. לכשיהיב
הוי קידושין. lich'yaiv havei kiddushin. When you give the money it's קידושין.
kiddushin. השתא מיהא לא הוי קידושין. hashta miha lo havei kiddushin. Now
it's not. מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu? Now it's obvious what would be
a נפקא מינה, nafka mina, right? Everything we've been talking about until
now. איכא בינייהו שפשטה ידה וקיבלה קידושין מאחר. ika beinaihu she'pashatah yadah
ve'kibbelah kiddushin me'acher. She accepted קידושין kiddushin from another guy before he
gave her the two hundred זוז. zuz. לרב הונא לא הוי קידושין.
le'Rav Huna lo havei kiddushin. For רב הונא Rav Huna it's not
good because as long as he eventually gives her the money she's
married as of day one. לרב יהודה הוי קידושין. le'Rav Yehuda havei
kiddushin. According to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda she's married to the second
guy because she's not yet married to the first guy. ותנן נמי
גבי גיטין כי האי גוונא. u'snan nami gabei gittin ki hai gavna.
We have a similar משנה Mishnah by a גט. get. המוציא את
אשתו הרי זה גיטך על מנת שתתני לי מאתיים זוז. ha'mozi es
ishto harei zeh gittech al menas she'tisni li masayim zuz. Here's your
גט get on the condition you give me two hundred זוז. zuz.
Interesting who's giving whom? In our משנה Mishnah he's giving her, he
has to persuade her to marry him, and in the second case
she's giving him, she has to pay you know that's like now
of course sadly we have that case of extortion you know way
too frequently by גיטין. gittin. She has to pay him in order
to get the גט. get. When you give me the two hundred
זוז. zuz. הרי זו מגורשת והיא תתן. harei zo megureshes ve'hi titten.
So the משנה Mishnah says she's מגורשת megureshes as long as she
gives the money. איתמר, itmar, so when is she מגורשת? megureshes? רב
הונא אמר והוא יתן. Rav Huna amar ve'hu yitten. והיא תתן, ve-hi
titein, give it and then you're as of now. רב יהודה אמר
Rav Yehuda amar לכשתתן, likshe-titein, when it's given. רב הונא אמר Rav
Huna amar והיא תתן, ve-hi titein, תנאי הוי. tnai havei.
It's just a תנאי, tnai, מקיים תנאי ואזלא. mekayeim tnai ve-azla. She
fulfills her תנאי tnai whenever, and then she's divorced as of now.
רב יהודה אמר Rav Yehuda amar לכשתתן, likshe-titein, when she gives. וכי
יהיב ליה הוי גיטא, Vekhi yahiv lei havei gita, when she gives
it to the גט, get, התם לא הוי גיטא, hatam lo havei
gita, not now. מאי בינייהו, Mai beinaihu, what would be a נפקא
מינה? nafka mina? I mean the obvious נפקא מינה, nafka mina, let's
say she sleeps with somebody in the interim, but the גמרא gemara
is going to give a different
נפקא מינה. nafka mina. איכא בינייהו Ika beinaihu שבנתקרע הגט shenitkarea haget
או שאבד. o she-avad. The גט get is torn or lost before
she gives the money. לרב הונא הוי גיטא, Le-Rav Huna havei gita,
רב הונא Rav Huna is still fine. The תנאי tnai is fulfilled
whenever the תנאי tnai is filled, retroactively it's from the day the
גט get was given. ולרב יהודה לא הוי גיטא, Ule-Rav Yehuda lo
havei gita, according to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda not, because since it
only takes effect later, we've already discussed that when you do an
act now to take effect later, there needs to be some remnant
of that act present when it takes effect, and therefore the גט
get has to still be around. And if the גט get isn't
around, it won't take effect. וצריכא, U-tzricha, and you need to tell
me their debate in both scenarios, קידושין kiddushin and גיטין. gittin. דאי
אשמעינן גבי קידושין, De-ee ashmienan gabei kiddushin, had you just told me
the position by קידושין, kiddushin, בהא קאמר רב הונא, be-ha ka-amar Rav
Huna, that's where רב הונא Rav Huna says it means as of
now, משום דלקירובי קאתי, mishum de-lekarvei ka-ati, you're trying to marry her,
so you want to do it as soon as possible. אבל גירושין
דלרחובי קאתי, Aval geirushin de-lerachokei ka-ati, but גירושין geirushin which is about
divorce and you're trying, you know, and you know who knows people
maybe want to reconcile and, you know, we'll assume that they're less
eager to do it right away. In that case, אימא מודי ליה
לרב יהודה, eima modei lei le-Rav Yehuda, maybe he'll agree to רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda that I will read it as a when. Again,
this is so interesting that the exact same technical language could mean
one thing by קידושין, kiddushin, one thing by גיטין. gittin. This gets
to the question of am I trying to figure out what you
indeed you know in your inner recesses of your heart mean, or
am I trying to figure out what the legal meaning of the
phrase is? Okay, but if it's what you're thinking, maybe it would
have been different between קידושין kiddushin and גיטין. gittin. ואי איתמר בהא,
Ve-ee itmar be-ha, had you told it to me just by גיטין,
gittin, בהא קאמר רב הונא, be-ha ka-amar Rav Huna, that's where רב
הונא Rav Huna says that it is as of now. What's the
logic to say the flip of what we just said? משום דאיהו
לא כסיף ליה למתבעה, Mishum de-ihu lo kasif lei le-mitbah, because he
can say I'll divorce her now and I'll be able to get
the two hundred זוז zuz eventually. I don't have to hold it
over her head that it won't take effect. I mean, it's still
not going to take effect, it's still תנאי, tnai, but I don't
have to make it postpone the effect. If I want the money
sooner, I'll just, you know, demand it from her, I'll bring her
to court. אבל הכא דאיכספא לה למתבעיה, Aval hacha de-ichasfa lah le-mitbahyei,
here, you know, because again of the gender dynamics, she'll be more
embarrassed to ask for the money. So since she'll be more embarrassed
to ask for the money, she might say I'm not going to
agree to marry him until I get the money. I'm not so
sure he's going to give me the money and I won't be
able to ask for it. So here, by interesting, like here we're
focusing on her דעת, da'at, not his דעת, da'at, right? Because before
the question was whose, I mean, in a קידושין kiddushin it's dependent
on both of their דעת. da'at. So here she might decide, you
know what, I'm not going to agree to marry this guy until
I actually get the money. אימא מודי ליה לרב יהודה, Eima modei
lei le-Rav Yehuda, so maybe you agree to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
that we'll interpret it to mean later. צריכא, Tzricha, you need to
tell me both. But at the end of the day, presumably, we're
not trying to guess what you happen to have in your head
at any particular time. We're just making a basic statement that this
term means one or the other. Either it means מעכשיו me'achshav or
it means לאחר זמן. le-achar zman. Okay, let's try to look at
one case about this. מיתיבי, Meitivei, I'll ask you on this. הרי
זה גיטך על מנת שתתני לי מאתים זוז, Harei zeh gitech al
menat she-titni li matayim zuz, אף על פי שנתקרע הגט או שאבד,
af al pi she-nitkarea haget o she-avad, הרי זו מגורשת. harei zu
megureshet. Okay, here's your גט get if you give me two hundred
זוז, zuz, even if it gets torn, she's divorced. So that's once
the money is given. So that sounds very clear like רב הונא
Rav Huna that it means מעכשיו. me'achshav. ואחר לא תנשא עד שתתן,
Ve-acher lo tinasei ad she-titein, but don't run and get married to
another guy until you give the money. Now, that doesn't mean because
it's not מעכשיו, me'achshav, it just means you better make sure that
you're able to fulfill the תנאי. tnai. If you never fulfill the
תנאי, tnai, you're never divorced, okay? But so don't go ahead and
act on it until you've done the תנאי. tnai. But technically speaking,
you're divorced as of now. Okay, that's a pretty big proof to
רב הונא. Rav Huna. ותניא, Ve-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא: braita:
אמר לה הרי זה גיטך על מנת שתתני לי מאתים זוז, Amar
lah harei zeh gitech al menat she-titni li matayim zuz, here's your
גט get if you give me two hundred זוז, zuz, ומת, u-met,
and he dies. נתנה אין זקוקה ליבם. Natna ein zekuka le-yavam.
If she gave it before he died and fulfilled the תנאי, tnai,
then she's divorced, she doesn't have to do יבום. yibum. לא נתנה
זקוקה ליבם, Lo natna zekuka le-yavam, otherwise she has to do יבום,
yibum, it wasn't fulfilled. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר: Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer: נותנת לאחיו או לאביו או לאחד מן הקרובים. notenet le-achiv
o le-aviv o le-achad min ha-krovim.
You don't have to give it to him. Yes, he's dead, but
you can still fulfill the תנאי, tnai, give it to a relative.
So what's the debate? So the גמרא gemara says: עד כאן לא
פליגי אלא דמר סבר לי ולא ליורשי, Ad kan lo peligi ela
de-mar savar li ve-lo le-yorshai, when you say give me, I mean
me, I don't mean my relatives, not my heirs. ומר סבר אפילו
ליורשי, U-mar savar afilu le-yorshai, it includes heirs.
But the only debate is, is it considered like you fulfilled it
when you gave it to an heir? But everybody would agree that
if it meant give it to my heir, it would work even
though the guy was already dead. So even though it was satisfied
only after the guy was dead, it still works because it took
effect retroactively when he originally gave the גט. get.
דכולי עלמא מיהא
תנאי הוי,
De-kulei alma
miha
tnai havei,
everybody agrees that it's a תנאי tnai and if you fulfill the
תנאי, tnai, it takes effect retroactively to when he originally gave the
גט. get. Two very clear ברייתות braitas supporting רב הונא. Rav Huna.
תיובתא דרב יהודה, Tiyuvta d'Rav Yehuda, clear contradiction to רב יהודה. Rav
Yehuda. אמר לך רב יהודה, Amar lach Rav Yehuda, רב יהודה Rav
Yehuda would tell you, הא מני רבי היא. Ha mani Rabbi hi.
Yes, this is רבי. Rabbi. There is a position that it means
מעכשיו. me'achshav. דאמר רב הונא אמר רבי, D'amar Rav Huna amar Rabbi,
רבי Rabbi would say, כל האומר על מנת כאומר מעכשיו דמי. Kol
ha'omer al mnat k'omer me'achshav dami. When you say "on the condition,"
it means "as of now." So you're right, those ברייתות braitas are
רבי, Rabbi, maybe our משנה mishna is רבי. Rabbi. Yes, there is
that position. ופליגי רבנן עליה, U'plegi rabanan alei, but I assert without
any evidence that there's that there's another opinion of the רבנן rabanan
that disagree and say it means לאחר זמן, l'achar zman, ואנא דאמי
כרבנן, v'ana dami k'rabanan, and I say like those other positions. Okay,
גופא, Gufa, let's see this statement. אמר רב הונא אמר רב, Amar
Rav Huna amar Rav, כל האומר על מנת כאומר מעכשיו דמי. Kol
ha'omer al mnat k'omer me'achshav dami. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira,
אמר רבי, amar Rabbi, רבי Rabbi would say it's כמעכשיו דמי. k'me'achshav
dami. אמר רב זירא, Amar Rav Zeira, רב זירא Rav Zeira said,
כי הוינא בבבל, Ki havina b'Vavel, you know, when I was in
בבל, Bavel, הוינא רמינא הא דרב הונא אמר רבי, Havina ramina ha
d'Rav Huna amar Rabbi, כל האומר על מנת כאומר מעכשיו דמי, kol
ha'omer al mnat k'omer me'achshav dami, that this statement that רבי Rabbi
said it means מעכשיו, me'achshav, ופליגי רבנן עליה. U'plegi rabanan alei. In
בבל Bavel we said that there was an opinion of the רבנן
rabanan that disagreed with it. We didn't know who they were, but
we just believed that this was only רבי's Rabbi's opinion. כי סליק
להתם, Ki salik l'hatam, when I went over there to ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and made עליה, aliyah, אשכחיה לרבי אסי, ashchayei l'Rabbi Assi,
I saw רב אסי, Rav Assi, דיתיב וקאמר לה משמיה דרבי יוחנן,
d'yatvei v'ka'amar lah mishmei d'Rabbi Yochanan, and was saying the following in
the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. הכל מודים באומר על מנת
כאומר מעכשיו דמי. Hakol modim b'omer al mnat k'omer me'achshav dami. Everybody
agrees!
It's not just רבי's Rabbi's opinion, which is like רב הונא, Rav
Huna, right? Don't claim, oh yes, yes, yes, you have all those
משניות mishnayot and ברייתות, braitas, but there's a רבנן rabanan that argue
on it. Nobody argues on it! Everybody says it means מעכשיו. me'achshav.
לא נחלקו, Lo nechelku, the only debate of whether you mean now
or later was what we just got through discussing, מהיום ולאחר מיתה.
Me'hayom u'l'achar misa. Okay, it's only when you say "as of now"
and לאחר מיתה. l'achar misa. But על מנת? Al mnat? על מנת
Al mnat means a תנאי. tnai. The question of
now תנאי tnai or or מעכשיו, me'achshav, now or later, is when
you didn't say על מנת, al mnat, you said "and." Okay, והתניא,
V'hatanya, and here's the ברייתא. braita. מהיום ולאחר מיתה Me'hayom u'l'achar misa
גט ואינו גט, get v'eino get, דברי חכמים. divrei Chachamim. We don't
know if it's a גט, get, we don't know if it means
now or later. רבי אומר כזה גט. Rabbi omer kazei get. רבי
Rabbi says it is. Okay, so all the evidence is על מנת
al mnat is מעכשיו. me'achshav. Don't claim that it's a position of
רבי Rabbi and the רבנן rabanan argue, there's no evidence that רבנן
rabanan argue on this. The only debate is around the discussion of
מהיום ולאחר מיתה. me'hayom u'l'achar misa. Okay, and now we'll just end
this, see, you didn't think we would get this far. ולרב יהודה
דאמר בעל מנת נמי פליגי, U'l'Rav Yehuda d'amar b'al mnat nami plegi,
according to רב יהודה Rav Yehuda that says that the debate is,
which is now what all the evidence, I mean רב יהודה, Rav
Yehuda, the debate that
even the רבנן rabanan even argue on רבי Rabbi by על מנת
al mnat and they say it means later, עד דמפליג ממהיום ולאחר
מיתה, Ad d'maflig mi'me'hayom u'l'achar misa, why is the only ברייתא braita
in the case of מהיום ולאחר מיתה? me'hayom u'l'achar misa? ליפלוג בעל
מנת, Liflog b'al mnat, argue in the על מנת! al mnat! Tell
me that even in an על מנת, al mnat, you, the רבנן,
rabanan, still think it means later if that's really
true. להודיעך כוחו דרבי, Lehodi'acha kocho d'Rabbi, to tell you how strong
רבי's Rabbi's position is. דמהיום ולאחר מיתה, D'me'hayom u'l'achar misa, even when
you don't say על מנת, al mnat, even when you say now
and לאחר מיתה, l'achar misa, where we would think it definitely means
some degree later, נמי הרי זה גט, nami harei zeh get, that
רבי Rabbi is prepared to say even when you say now and
later it means as of now. וליפלוג בעל מנת להודיעך כוחו דרבנן?
V'liflog b'al mnat lehodi'acha kocho d'rabanan? But okay, tell us that even
in an על מנת al mnat case, the רבנן rabanan say it
means later, okay, and not now, why not tell us both debate?
כוח דהיתרא עדיף. Koach d'hetera adif. No, no, רבי's Rabbi's position is
stronger. Why is it stronger? Because if you say "as of now,"
that always means it's more likely to take effect, right? You're more
likely, and if it's a גט, get, you're more likely to permit
her. Right, if you say it means later, then it won't necessarily
take effect later, you might not have all the conditions later. So
we did that a little quick, but bottom line is, is that
when you say מהיום ולאחר מיתה, me'hayom u'l'achar misa, it's a very
ambiguous statement. And there it's possible it means now, possible it means
later. רבי Rabbi says it definitely means now, רבי Rabbi says it
means מעכשיו. me'achshav. When you say על מנת, al mnat, it seems
very clear you mean מעכשיו. me'achshav. All the evidence is מעכשיו, me'achshav,
and therefore, you know, it seems very, very clear that means מעכשיו.
me'achshav. And the only argument is, no, no, even there רבי Rabbi
and the רבנן rabanan disagree. Okay, but that's really a questionable statement.
It seems like that case might be unanimous, that that means מעכשיו.
me'achshav. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda would like to believe that that case
could also mean לאחר זמן, l'achar zman, but all the evidence is
that in the על מנת al mnat it means מעכשיו me'achshav and
nobody disagrees with that. Okay, so we'll end with that.